## Nicolò Martini

Senior PHP Developer - London nicolo.martini.io

#### **PROFILE**

An experienced programmer, mainly in PHP, with a good knowledge of many mainstream languages. I am a functional language fan, and I love Scala. I have a very good knowledge of state-of-the-art PHP and Web technologies.

I love abstraction and code quality, always trying to write elegant and beautiful code that meets customer expectations.

I am an open source enthusiast, and I publish my code on GitHub whenever I can.

## **SKILLS AND EXPERTISE**

- 10+ years experience in PHP and Web development. PHP 5.4, 5.5 and 5.6. Symfony, Silex, Laravel, Phalcon, Silverstripe, Composer, PSR-0...PSR-4
- Strong understanding of strengths and weaknesses of OOP, strong OOP architectural skills.
- Best practices, design patterns, functional programming
- HML5, CSS3, LESS, Javascript, JQuery, AngularJS, GruntJS, REST, HTTP standards
- Code Refactoring, TDD, BDD, Continuous integration, Agile
- Linux/Mac Os X, Apache/NGINX, Vagrant, VirtualBox, Docker, Git administration
- Open to work with non PHP languages, with a preference for statically typed ones (Scala over all, Haskell)

# **EDUCATION**

Master Degree in Mathematics (Magna cum Laude) Bachelor Degree in Mathematics (Magna cum Laude)

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# Senior PHP Developer: DXI Ltd

March 2014 - Current

Developed high-scalable PHP applications in different frameworks (Laravel, Phalcon, Symfony components) in a highly distributed, traffic intensive environment (millions phone calls per day made by the software).

Key Experiences:

- Implemented OAuth2 authentication system for the platform
- Designed level 3 RESTful APIs with custom mime-types and hypermedia controls, in a functional style
- Halved memory and CPU footprint migrating the main application from Laravel to Phalcon
- Fixed years long standing and critical security bugs in first couple of months
- Team leading, mentoring/helping junior developers.

PHP Developer: Comperio s.r.l

August 2011 - March 2014

Nicolò Martini nicmartnic@gmail.com http://github.com/nicmart Lead developer of DNG, an OPAC software that serves almost a thousand of libraries. It is the second most used OPAC software in Italy, and it is by far the most technologically advanced within its competitors. DNG is written in PHP and it is built on top of the Silverstripe CMS. Key Experiences:

- solved the problem of heterogeneus data sources with a data layer to uniformly access library data from different sources (MySQL, SOAP, SOLR)
- definition of a context free language for OPAC queries
- Turbomarc (a dialect of UNIMARC) transformation layer for extracting data from SOLR documents
- implemented a really powerful shelf and saved-searches system for user and librarians
- improved dramatically the reactivity of the application with a semantically event-driven client-side code, modularized through RequireJS
- used GruntJS for the build process (composer, css/js minification, less compilation, etc.)

# Fullstack Web Developer: ElectroYou.it

January 2005 - August 2011

ElectroYou is the italian community of electronics lovers and professionals, and it is one of the top websites in its field. It is written in PHP.

**Key Experiences:** 

- Dramatically improved user engagement with gamification (reputation and achievement system)
- Implemented an activity stream system and a powerful, multi-channel, notification system
- Integrated several open source projects (PhpBB, Mediawiki, Symfony components)
- Implemented a driver that transforms FidoCadJ code (a Cad for electronic schematics) embedded in forum posts to PNG.

## **OPEN SOURCE**

StringTemplate - <a href="http://github.com/nicmart/StringTemplate">http://github.com/nicmart/StringTemplate</a>
A string interpolation library. +10 000 installs in Packagist, used by box.com

Tree - <a href="https://github.com/nicmart/Tree">https://github.com/nicmart/Tree</a>
A Tree data structure in PHP, +5000 installs in Packagist

Denote Constitution of the Market Constitution of the Constitution

DomainSpecificQuery - <a href="http://github.com/nicmart/DomainSpecificQuery">http://github.com/nicmart/DomainSpecificQuery</a>
Build and define domain-specific queries and compile them into other formats

Functionals - <a href="http://github.com/nicmart/Functionals">http://github.com/nicmart/Functionals</a> Higher-order functions for PHP

UniversalMatcher - <a href="http://github.com/nicmart/UniversalMatcher">http://github.com/nicmart/UniversalMatcher</a> A rule based matcher engine for PHP

#### **CERTIFICATIONS**

- Automata (Coursera)
- Algorithms (Coursera)

Nicolò Martini nicmartnic@gmail.com http://github.com/nicmart http://nicolo.martini.io @nicmartnic Linkedin